<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mākarappi grant of Pulakeśin II</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>EpiDoc encoding</resp>
               <persName ref="part:daba">
                  <forename>Dániel</forename>
                  <surname>Balogh</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
               <persName ref="part:daba">
                  <forename>Dániel</forename>
                  <surname>Balogh</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">CalE01-Makarappi-Pulakesin2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Dániel Balogh.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><!-- only the handDesc can be filled in at this stage -->
            <msDesc><!-- //// NB: the msIdentifier had to be added for validation purposes ///. It will be edited later with the metadata spreadsheet -->
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                  <idno/>
                  <!-- don't modify this -->
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents><!-- describe the intellectual content of an inscription -->
                  <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary>
                  <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <p>The halanta T in L26 is not quite clear in the scan but seems to be a small subscript ta complete with loop, probably with a short vertical, not horizontal, line above it.</p>
                     <p>The final punctuation mark (not transcribed by Fleet) is a single horizontal stroke with a strong bulge upward and to the left, like a ? without the dot, rotated 90° counterclockwise. (Perhaps classify as a minimalist spiral mangala sign of the  The punctuation mark after mahībhr̥tāṁ in line 5, not shown by Fleet, is faint and located below the anusvāra.</p>
                     <p>There are two different kinds of r̥ mātrā; one resembles subscript r̥ but with more of a curl at the end and not extending back up into body space (what I know as a regular r̥ mark; e.g. l2 mātr̥bhiḥ, mātr̥bhir, l4 bhr̥tāṁ l5 °āvabhr̥tha), and another that bends downward, sort of resembling a subscript l (l4 kr̥tā°; l27 kr̥ṣṇāhayo). Is this driven by the consonant to which r̥ is attached? There are also two forms of ka: the regular form and what may be a cursive one, where the upper part looks like a mirrored Z. Some of these (l1, kārttikeyā°; l4, kariṣṇu) follow anusvāras and could have been intended for ṅk, but the same shape is fould in l12, śaka. 
                <!-- The script name(s) will be inserted here at a later stage from the metadata spreasheet. At this stage, you can mention here in a free-text paragraph any characteristics of the writing observed more than once in this inscription that seem unusual/uncommon or otherwise noteworthy given the general characteristics of the script in question. See EG 11.2. --></p>
                     <!-- If you need to identify individual hands (EG §7.5/) in addition to one or more paragraphs of general palaeographic description, wrap <summary> around the <p> or <p>s above, and, outside <summary>, create <handNote> elements for each hand as follows:
            <summary><p><p/></summary>
            <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand1"></handNote>
            <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand2"></handNote>
           -->
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
                        under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
                        agreement no 809994).</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <schemaRef type="guide"
                    key="EGDv01"
                    url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="bib"
                       matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
               <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named
                            ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="part"
                       matchPattern="([a-z]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
               <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the
                            <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_V01.xml</ref> file.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:axja" when="2020-11-03" status="draft">Updating toward the encoding template v03</change>
         <change who="part:daba" when="2020-03-02" status="draft">Initial encoding of the file</change>
         <change who="part:daba" when="2020-08-12" status="draft">Updated to template v2, encoded bibliography.</change>
         <!-- Add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn">
<pb n="1r"/>
<p>
<pb n="1v"/>
<lb n="1"/>svasti śrīmatāṁ sakal<choice><sic>o</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>-bhuvana-saṁstūyamāna-mānavya-sagotrāṇāṁ <orig>hārītī</orig>-putrāṇāṁ sa<lb n="2" break="no"/>pta-loka-mātr̥bhiḥ sapta-mātr̥bhir abhivarddhitānāṁ<g type="circleLow">.</g> kārttikeyānugraha-parirakṣaṇa-prā<lb n="3" break="no"/>pta-kalyāṇa-paraṁparāṇāṁ bhagavan-nārāyaṇa-prasāda-samāsādita-varāha-lā<lb n="4" break="no"/><space type="binding-hole"/>ñchanekṣaṇa-vaśī-kr̥tāśeṣa-mahībhr̥tāṁ<unclear><g type="circleLow">.</g></unclear> <orig>calikyānāṁ</orig> kulam alaṁkariṣṇ<choice><sic>u</sic><corr>oḥ</corr></choice> <lb n="5"/><space type="binding-hole"/>Aśvamedhāvabhr̥tha-snāna-pavitrī-kr̥ta-gātrasya satyāśraya-śrī<lb n="6" break="no"/>-polekeśi-vallabha-mahārājasya pautraḥ parākramākrānta-vanavā<orig>ś</orig>yādi-para-nr̥<lb n="7" break="no"/>pati-maṇḍala-pratibaddha-viśuddha-kīrtti-patākasya kīrttivarmma-vallabha-mahā<lb n="8" break="no"/>rājasya tanayo naya-vinayādi-guṇa-vibhūty-āśrayaḥ śrī-satyā<pb n="2r" break="no"/><lb n="9" break="no"/>śraya-p<orig>ri</orig>thivī-vallabha-mahārājaḥ samara-śata-saṁghaṭṭa-saṁsakta-para-<unclear reason="eccentric_ductus">n</unclear>r̥pati-parā<lb n="10" break="no"/>jayopalabdha-parameśvarāpara-nāmadheyaḥ sarvvān ājñāpayaty</p>
<p>astu v<unclear>o</unclear> viditaṁ ma<lb n="11" break="no"/>yā vātāpī-nagarīm adhitiṣṭhatātmanaḥ pravarddhamāna-rājyābhiṣeka-saṁvatsare tr̥tī<lb n="12" break="no"/><space type="binding-hole"/>ye śaka-nr̥pati-saṁvatsara-śateṣu catustriṁśā<unclear>dh</unclear>ikeṣu pañcasv at<unclear>ī</unclear>teṣu bhādra<lb n="13" break="no"/><space type="binding-hole"/>padāmāvāsyāyāṁ sūryya-grahaṇa-nimitta<unclear>ṁ</unclear> mātā-pitror ātmanaḥ puṇyā<lb n="14" break="no"/><space type="binding-hole"/>vāptaye vāsiṣṭha-sagotrāya taittirīyāya tagarādhivāsine<lb n="15"/>catur-vvedāyoṁbarakheḍa-kula-nāmadheyāya jyeṣṭhaśarmmaṇe rolku<lb n="16" break="no"/>ṟuky-uttarataḥ kadappa-grāma-dakṣiṇataḥ mākarappir nnāma grāmaḥ
<pb n="2v"/>
<lb n="17"/>sanidhiḥ sopanidhiḥ sakl̥ptaḥ soparikaraḥ pañca-mahā-yajña-nirvvāpa<lb n="18" break="no"/>ṇārttham udaka-pūrvvakaṁ dattaḥ</p>
<p>Ayam asmad-dāyo <supplied reason="subaudible">’</supplied>nyair āgāmi-nr̥patibhir anuma<lb n="19" break="no"/>ntavyo varddhanīyaś ca<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> yo vājñānād ajaram amaraṁ vātmānaṁ manyamāno <supplied reason="subaudible">’</supplied>pa<lb n="20" break="no"/><space type="binding-hole"/>haret sa pañca-mahā-pātaka-saṁyukta<orig>ḥ</orig> bahūni kalpa-saha<lb n="21" break="no"/><space type="binding-hole"/>srāṇi narakaṁ vasati<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> yaḥ pālayati tāny eva svarggaṁ vāsati<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied>
<lb n="22"/>Uktañ ca bhagavatā veda-vyāsena vyāsena
</p>
<lg n="1" met="anuṣṭubh">
   <l n="a">bahubhir vvasudhā bhuktā</l>
   <l n="b"><lb n="23"/>rājabhis sagarādibhiḥ</l>
   <l n="c">yasya yasya yadā bhūmis</l>
   <l n="d">tasya tasya <pb n="3r"/><lb n="24"/>tadā phala<orig>ṁ</orig></l>
</lg>
<lg n="2" met="anuṣṭubh">
   <l n="a">sva-dattāṁ para-dattāṁ vā</l>
   <l n="b">yatnād rakṣa yudhiṣṭhira</l>
   <l n="c">mahīṁ mahī<lb n="25" break="no"/>matāṁ śreṣṭha<surplus>ṁ</surplus></l>
   <l n="d">dānāc cchreyo <supplied reason="subaudible">’</supplied>nupālana<orig>ṁ</orig></l>
</lg>
<lg n="3" met="anuṣṭubh">
   <l n="a">ṣaṣṭim varṣa-sahasrāṇi</l>
   <l n="b">svargge <lb n="26"/>modati bhūmi-daḥ</l>
   <l n="c">Ācch<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>e</corr></choice>ttā cānumantā ca</l>
   <l n="d">tāny eva narake vaseT</l>
</lg>
<lg n="4" met="anuṣṭubh">
   <l n="a">vindhyā<lb n="27" break="no"/><space type="binding-hole"/>ṭavīṣv atoyāsu</l>
   <l n="b">śuṣka-koṭara-vāsinaḥ</l>
   <l n="c">kr̥ṣṇāhayo hi jā<lb n="28" break="no"/>yante</l>
   <l n="d">bhūmi-dānaṁ haranti ye<g type="circleHigh">.</g></l>
</lg>
<lg n="5" met="indravajrā">
   <l n="a">dattāni yānīha purā narendraiḥ</l>
   <l n="b">dānāni dha<lb n="29" break="no"/>rmmārttha-yaśas-karāṇi<space/></l>
   <l n="c">nirmālya-vānta-pratimāni tāni<space/></l>
   <l n="d">ko nāma sā<lb n="30" break="no" style="text-align: center"/>dhuḫ punar ādadīta<surplus>ḥ</surplus><g type="circleHigh">.</g></l>
</lg>
<ab>Iti<g type="dashConvex">.</g>
</ab>
<pb n="3v"/>
         </div>
         <div type="apparatus">
               <listApp>
                  <app loc="2">
                     <lem>abhivarddhitānāṁ<g type="circleLow">.</g></lem>
                     <note>The uninterpretable character after <foreign>abhivarddhitānāṁ</foreign> is a circle like an <foreign>anusvāra</foreign>, but at baseline level. It may be a correction mark to the alternative shape of <foreign>k</foreign> in the next character (see Commentary), or possibly a space filler added subsequently where the scribe spaced characters too widely (along with what is read as a superfluous <foreign>visarga</foreign> in line 8). </note>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="6">
                     <lem>-polekeśi-</lem>
                     <rdg source="bib:Fleet1877_01">-polikeśi-</rdg>
                     <note>The second character is very different from that of <foreign>calikyānāṁ</foreign>: it lacks the extended tail (like the cursive <foreign>lo</foreign>) and has no clear <foreign>i</foreign> <foreign>mātrā</foreign>. I am quite certain it is <foreign>le</foreign>.</note>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="8">
                     <lem>-vibhū<surplus><unclear>ḥ</unclear></surplus>ty-</lem>
                     <rdg source="bib:Fleet1877_01">°vibhū<surplus>ṁ</surplus>ty°</rdg>
                     <note>The circle Fleet transcribes as a superfluous <foreign>anusvāra</foreign> is at headline height, whereas all other <foreign>anusvāra</foreign>s are well above, including that in <foreign>laṁ</foreign> (l4), which is to the right of the character. (The <foreign>anusvāra</foreign> of <foreign>saṁvatsare</foreign>, l11, is practically at baseline height and to the right of <foreign>sa</foreign>, but that is because of <foreign>stu</foreign> hanging down from above. Here there is nothing preventing the circle being higher.) There is probably another mark below this circle at baseline height, so if it is a superfluous character, then it is probably a <foreign>visarga</foreign>. Neither the circle, nor the fainter, comma-like mark below are visible in Sir Walter Elliot's estampage.</note>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="9">
                     <lem>-p<orig>ri</orig>thivī-</lem>
                     <rdg source="bib:Fleet1877_01">pr̥thivī</rdg>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="14">
                     <lem>rolku<lb n="16" break="no"/>ṟuky-</lem>
                     <rdg source="bib:Fleet1877_01">rolkū<lb n="16" break="no"/>ṟuky-</rdg>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="15">
                     <lem>°kheḍa-</lem>
                     <rdg source="bib:Fleet1877_01">°khe<choice><sic>da</sic><corr>ḍa</corr></choice>-</rdg>
                     <note>Fleet tentatively emends to <note>ḍa</note>, but the character seems to be <note>ḍa</note> to begin with.</note>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="27">
                     <lem>hi</lem>
                     <rdg source="bib:Fleet1877_01">pi</rdg>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="28">
                     <lem>ye<g type="circleHigh">.</g></lem>
                     <note>A circle or dot at headline height at the end of the stanza, possibly signifying a change of metre?</note>
                  </app>
                  <app loc="30">
                     <lem>ādadīta<surplus>ḥ</surplus><g type="circleHigh">.</g></lem>
                     <note>Again a circle at headline height, though slightly lower than the upper part of the <foreign>visarga</foreign>. I believe this is another punctuation mark, though I agree with Fleet that the two dots on the left are a superfluous <foreign>visarga</foreign> (i.e. the punctuation mark does not consist of three dots, only the one on the right).</note>
                  </app>
               </listApp>

         </div>
         <div type="translation" source="bib:Fleet1877_01">
<p n="1-10">Hail! The grandson of the Great King <persName>Satyāśraya-Śrī-Polikeśivallabha</persName>,
   whose body was purified by ablutions performed after celebrating horse-sacrifices, and who adorned the family of the glorious <persName>Calikyas</persName>,
   who are of the kindred of <persName>Mānavya</persName> which is praised over the whole world,
   and who are the descendants of <persName>Hāritī</persName>[sic],
   and who have been nourished by seven mothers who are the seven mothers of mankind,
   and who have attained an uninterrupted continuity of prosperity by the favour and protection of <persName>Kārttikeya</persName>,
   and who have had all kings made subject to them by the mere sight of the sign<note>Crest, signet, or ensign.</note> of the Boar which they acquired through the favour of the holy <persName>Nārāyaṇa</persName>;—
   the son of the Great King <persName>Kīrttivarmavallabha</persName>[sic], the banner of whose pure fame was hung up in the territories of the hostile kings of <persName>Vanavāsī</persName> and other countries that had been invaded by his prowess;—
   the favourite of the world, the Great King <persName>Śrī-Satyāśraya</persName>,—
   who is the abode of the power of statesmanship and humility and other good qualities, and who has acquired the second name of ‘Supreme Lord’ by victory over hostile kings who applied themselves to the contest of a hundred battles,—
   issues his commands to all people:—</p>
<p n="10-22">“Be it known to you that, five hundred and thirty-four of the years of the <persName>Śaka</persName> king having elapsed, in the third year of my own installation in the sovereignty, on the day of the new-moon of <supplied reason="subaudible">the month</supplied> Bhādrapada,  on account of an eclipse of the sun, in order that my parents may acquire my own religious merit,
   the village of <placeName>Mākarappi</placeName>, with its treasures and deposits and assignments and major taxes,<note resp="part:daba">Fleet notes he is uncertain about translating <foreign>kl̥pta</foreign> and <foreign>uparikara</foreign>.</note>  to the north of <supplied reason="subaudible">the village of</supplied> <placeName>Rolkūṟuki</placeName>  and to the south of the village of <placeName>Kadappa</placeName>, has been given by me, while governing <supplied reason="subaudible">at</supplied> the city of <placeName>Vātāpīnagarī</placeName>,
   with libations of water, for the purpose of celebrating the five great sacrifices, to <persName>Jyeṣṭhaśarmā</persName>,
   whose family name is <persName>Umbarakheda</persName>, of the kindred of <persName>Vāsiṣṭha</persName>, and of the school of the <persName>Taittirīyas</persName>, an inhabitant of <supplied reason="subaudible">the city of</supplied> <placeName>Tagara</placeName>,<note>Probably the ancient city mentioned by the author of the Periplus and Ptolemy, and of which the remains may be traced over a wide area, on the plateau to the south of Rozah, about four miles from Daulatābād (formerly Devagiri), not far from the cave temples of Elora. [Fleet's editor in IA]</note>
   who is acquainted with the four Vedas. This my gift should be recognized and increased by other kings who may come after me. He shall incur the guilt of the five great sins and shall dwell for many thousands of ages in hell, who, through ignorance or because he esteems himself incapable of decay or immortal, may confiscate it; he, who preserves it, shall dwell for the same duration of time in heaven!”
   And it has been said by the holy <persName>Vyāsa</persName>, the arranger of the Vedas:—</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="1">Land has been enjoyed by many kings, commencing with <persName>Sagara</persName>, &amp;c.! </p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="2">O <persName>Yudhiṣṭhira</persName>, best of kings!, carefully preserve land that has been given, whether by thyself or by another; preservation <supplied reason="subaudible">of a grant</supplied> is better than making a grant!</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="3"> He, who bestows land, enjoys happiness in heaven for sixty thousand years; he, who revokes <supplied reason="subaudible">a grant</supplied> or connives at such an act, shall dwell for the same number of years in hell!</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="4"> They, who confiscate a grant of land, are born as black serpents, dwelling in dried-up hollow trees in the forests of the <placeName>Vindhya</placeName> mountains, which are destitute of water!</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="5">What good man would resume those gifts which have been made in former times by kings, and which produce piety and wealth and fame, but which <supplied reason="subaudible">if revoked</supplied>, are like the remains of an oblation that are vomited forth?!<note resp="part:daba">I’m not sure I understand Fleet’s translation here, but surely the point of this stock verse is that re-granting land is like reusing a ceremonial garland or re-eating vomit.</note></p>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="fra" source="bib:Estienne-Monod2008_01">
<p n="1-22">Prospérité ! le petit-fils du grand roi illustre Satyāśraya Polikeśin Vallabha, dont le corps fut lavé par le bain purificatoire de l’aśvamedha,
   ornement de la lignée des Calukya, illustres, honorés dans l’univers entier, de la même lignée que les descendants de Manu, fils de Hāritī,
   choyés par les sept Mères, mères des sept mondes, eux qui acquirent une prospérité ininterrompue par la faveur et la protection de Kārtikeya,
   qui se rendirent maîtres de tous les rois, soumis par la vue du signe du sanglier, grâce obtenue de l’illustre Nārāyaṇa, le fils du grand roi Kīrtivarman Vallabha, qui dressa les bannières <supplied reason="subaudible">proclamant</supplied> sa gloire immaculée dans les royaumes des rois ennemis de Vanavāsī et des autres <supplied reason="subaudible">villes</supplied>, vaincues par sa vaillance,
   le grand roi illustre Satyāśraya Pr̥thivī Vallabha, 
   en qui trouve refuge<note>Ce composé glose le biruda satyāśraya.</note> l’art de diriger, la modestie et d’autres vertus, ainsi que la puissance,
   qui reçut pour autre nom celui de Parameśvara car il avait vaincu les rois ennemis engagés dans les heurts de centaines de batailles, ordonne à tous : 
   qu’il soit connu de vous que, me trouvant dans la ville de Vātāpī, lors de la troisième année après ma consécration sur l’auguste trône, cinq cent trente quatre années s’étant écoulées dans l’ère Śaka,
   pour le sacrifice de la nouvelle lune du mois de Bhādra, à l’occasion d’une éclipse de soleil, en vue de l’acquisition des mérites de ma mère, de mon père ainsi que des miens,
   je donne à Jyeṣṭhaśarman, du même gotra que Vāsiṣṭha, de l’école de Taittirīya, habitant Tagara, maîtrisant les quatre Veda, dont le nom de famille est Oṁbarakheda, un village du nom de Mākarappi, au nord de Rolkūṟuki, au sud du village de Kadappa, avec ses trésors,<note>D. C. Sircar, 1966, p. 30.</note> exempté des taxes de reversion,<note>ibid., p.405 : dépôt qui reste la propriété du donataire.</note> avec les taxes régulières<note>ibid., p. 159 : impôt fixé en fonction d’un revenu.</note> et les taxes irrégulières,<note>ibid., p. 406 : taxe additionnelle.</note>
   après avoir fait une libation d’eau, pour que soient offerts les cinq grands sacrifices. Ce don que nous faisons doit être approuvé et augmenté par les autres rois à venir. Celui qui, soit par ignorance, soit parce qu’il pense n’être sous l’emprise ni de la vieillesse ni de la mort, prend <supplied reason="subaudible">une terre</supplied>, est lié aux cinq grands crimes et demeure en enfer pendant plusieurs milliers d’âges.
   Celui qui protège ces ordres-là demeure dans le ciel. Et le bienheureux Vyāsa, compilateur du Veda, l’a dit.</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="1">Beaucoup de rois ont joui de la terre, Sagara le premier, celui qui possède la terre en possède le fruit.</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="2">Qu’elle soit donnée par toi ou par un autre, ô Yudhiṣṭhira, protège la terre, ô meilleur des possesseurs de la terre, la préservation d’une terre est plus méritoire que le don !</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="3">Celui qui donne une terre se réjouit soixante mille années dans le ciel, que celui qui la prend ou le permet demeure aussi longtemps en enfer !</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="4">Habitant les grottes arides des rivages sauvages du Vindhya, ceux qui prennent la terre donnée renaissent serpents noirs !</p>
            <p rend="stanza" n="5">Autrefois en ce monde des rois firent des dons, qui engendrent dharma, artha et gloire,
semblables au reste de l’offrande que l’on recrache, quel homme de bien s’en emparerait ?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary"><p>Sir Walter Elliot's note accompanying his rubbings of these plates, preserved in several copies, goes as follows (with minor variation in the copies):
<q>Copper Sasanam of four plates recording the grant of the village of Makarappi between Caddapa and Rólkúr as a Shradda gift by Satyasreya Cháḷukya of Callian in the year SS_ 534 being the third of his reign. The Sasanam belongs to Mahendra Shanta a Jain Guru of Hyderabad. From General Fraser.</q></p>

         </div>
        <div type="bibliography">
           <p>First edited by J. F. Fleet (<bibl rend="omitname"><ptr target="bib:Fleet1877_01"/></bibl>) with inked rubbings and translation. Fleet reconsidered the date in <bibl><ptr target="bib:Fleet1888_02"/><citedRange unit="page">141</citedRange><citedRange unit="item">8</citedRange></bibl> and in <bibl><ptr target="bib:Fleet1891_03"/><citedRange>2-3</citedRange></bibl>. The present edition by Dániel Balogh is based on a collation of Fleet's text with his published facsimiles and inked impressions from Sir Walter Elliot's collection.<note>Scans of these impressions were obtained by Emmanuel Francis from the Edinburgh University Library, the Bibliothèque nationale de France and the British Museum.</note></p>
           <listBibl type="primary">
             <bibl n="JFF"><ptr target="bib:Fleet1877_01"/></bibl><!--SOCI 27-->
           </listBibl>
           <listBibl type="secondary">
             <bibl>
              <ptr target="bib:Fleet1888_02"/>
              <citedRange unit="page">141</citedRange>
              <citedRange unit="item">8</citedRange>
             </bibl>
             <bibl>
              <ptr target="bib:Fleet1891_03"/>
              <citedRange>2-3</citedRange>
             </bibl>
           </listBibl>
        </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
